Imagine having a DevOps teammate who never sleeps,
someone who can debug a failing deployment,
optimize Terraform modules, write Skaffold configuration,
enter CI pipelines, and that too instantly.
That's what Gemini brings to DevOps on Google Cloud.
Let's just see how we can do all that.
When you search for Gemini,
there are three Gemini tools that we can use as a DevOps.
The first one is Gemini Code Assist.
This is AI assisted coding inside VS Code and Cloud Workstation.
The second one is a Gemini Cloud Assist.
That is like an operational partner.
And the third one is a Gemini CLI.
Let's first start with the Code Assist.
So come down here and search for Code Assist.
Now inside the Gemini Code Assist, if you are doing for the first time,
you need to enable.
Now you have to select your billing account and let's
say continue to Admin for Gemini page.
Now select here the Standard, say Continue.
In the number of license, I'm choosing just one license and saying Continue.
Right now it is in trial mode,
so that's why the cost is saying $0 for the first month.
And let's say Complete purchase.
Now this will enable a Gemini Code Assist.
Now let's open up the VS Code and let's look for a plugin for Gemini.
Here you see Gemini Code Assist.
Let's install that app. Now this got installed successfully.
Now on the right side bottom corner, you see an option for Gemini.
Click on that.
Here you see Gemini Code Assist.
Let's say Enable.
Now it's asking for sign in, so let's sign in.
Say Open.
It got logged in.
Now it is asking me to select a cloud project, so I'm
selecting that. Here I can see all of them.
I'm selecting my specific hpc‑1 project, and now you can see that we are
successfully connected, and it can do a couple of things for me.
I have to just type in here the prompt.
For example, I can say Find the issues in my file,
and then it can start suggesting to me that what could be the
potential error and what I can do best with that.
Or maybe I can say here in my chat Generate a Cloud
Build pipeline that runs tests, builds a Docker image from a Dockerfile,
scan it for vulnerabilities, and pushes it to the Artifact Registry.
And let's go now.
You can see that it has started creating the code for us, and it
has written the cloudbuild.yaml completely.
You have to just say Accept,
and here you can see that code written for a Dockerfile as well and has
given us all the commands that need to be get executed.
So that's how Gemini Code Assist can help you to write the code,
to find the issues, and to improve the performance of your specific code.
Now on a similar line of the Code Assist, we have Gemini Cloud Assist as well.
You can just search here Cloud Assist. And if it is not enabled,
just click on Enable and enable the API for this Cloud Assist.
Now let's say you go down to our Cloud Workstation.
And on the top you can see Gemini Cloud Assist.
Click on that icon. That will open up a window for Gemini Cloud Assist,
and there you can start asking a question,
saying,
Explain my current cloud workstation. Even though I
have misspelled the explain spelling,
but still it is going to take it and give me the
explanation about my current Cloud Workstations.
It can help you to generate the Terraform scripts.
It can help you to debug the issues, and many more.
Here you can see that it has created the entire summary for me,
saying that the cluster name is this, location is this,
and entire information that is there in my Cloud Workstation.
Similarly,
I can open up my logs and I can debug the logs using this Cloud Assist as well.
Cloud Assist is available default in your entire cloud.
Wherever you go on that screen, on the top,
you can click on that icon of the Google Cloud Assist,
and that window is available.
You can start chatting and ask all your questions.
Not only this, in fact,
this Gemini Cloud Assist is also available in the CLI
where we call it Gemini Cloud CLI.
So let's open up our CLI, say Authorize.
In the Cloud Shell, you have to just type in Gemini,
and then the Gemini will appear where you can start typing your prompt
and you can take all the help from the Google CLI.
So that's how easy it is to use the Gemini in the CLI.
So overall, we have a lot of AI assistance there for DevOps.
As we have seen that,
we have the AIs assistant in the form of Code Assist that
you can integrate with the VS Code.
Cloud Assist automatically there,
which can help you for the operation purpose within your admin console itself.
And the third one is you have the Gemini AI Assistant
available within the Google Cloud CLI as well.